Welcome back to AM Northwest. If you love
shopping garage and estate sales, why
not make a business out of it? Here to
share expert tips on how to get started
selling your vintage wares, we welcome
back antique appraiser Gary Germer. Great
to see you, Gary. >> Hey Helen, thanks
for having me back. >> Okay, so this is
kind of an idea if you if it's something
you're passionate about, you love to
do, maybe make it into a business. >>
Oh yeah, and I think that's part of the
key of it is is it has to be something
you love because >> to love it. >> Yeah,
for sure. Because otherwise it becomes
a chore and that's what we're trying to
avoid. What you're doing already is the
chore. >> So let's first talk about the
difference between garage sales and
estate sales cuz they are very different.
>> Yeah, and you want to find your own
strategy of what works for you of what
you're dealing with. Garage sales
basically are are sales where people are
clearing out their house and it's the
junk they don't want. >> Exactly, yeah.
>> An estate sale implies somebody
there died or has downsized and they're
selling everything in the house. So the
chances are you're going to get a better
selection of really good things at an
estate sale as a general rule, but they're
usually professionally run so you're
probably going to have to pay higher
prices. Garage sales on the other hand,
the people may not know what they have.
So it's usually a lot cheaper stuff.
And so the ideal is to find the family
who's running their own estate sale and
>> There you go, that's right. Okay, so
you have a First tip is train your eye.
>> This is probably the If you don't
take away anything else, just that's the
biggest thing. You want to just train
your eyes to what is cool and what is
neat. In front of you there is a is a
whiskey glass and this is a case in
point. There was five of these. I had I
happened to go to an estate sale >> Mhm.
>> which I never do. I just happened to
go to this one. And in the kitchen were
five of these in a stack and they were
filthy dirty. They had been in the
cupboard for at least 30 years, had that
grime on it. >> Yeah. >> And um I thought
these are really cool. Now I didn't
look at what they were I just thought
those were kind of cool and they were $8
for the five. So I thought well I'll
I'll do $8 for them. I think they would
just be fun to have. >> Yeah.
>> So when I got them home
and I got it because I thought that they
looked great. I got them home, cleaned
them up, and we noticed a
mark on them is R. Lalique.
They're glass. I thought they might
have been a plastic type, but they're
crystal. R. Lalique means it was made
before 1940 by the Lalique company. I
thought, "Well, great. I got a score."
I'll see about maybe getting a couple
more to fill it out. Looked on eBay.
They sell for 400 bucks a piece. >> No.
>> On eBay. So, that was one of my you
know >> Wow. >> And it wasn't because I
was this big genius that I knew every
pattern of Lalique. I just thought it was
cool and it's because I've been at it and
it's unusual and I liked it and that's
the the what training your eye will do.
Good stuff will pop out at you. >> Okay.
And then you say to use your and use
a category that really interests you.
>> Exactly. And this is kind of like
this getting started. The problem is
there's so much out there. >> Yeah.
>> So, you can't become an expert on
everything. People People think I am, but
I I tell them that I really don't know
the value of every item ever made by man
>> Right. >> anywhere in the world at
any time in history off the top of my
head. >> I know you like I know you like
art. >> I do. I love art. I love a
lot of stuff. What I would suggest is
starting with smaller things. Like
jewelry is a big deal. >> Okay. >> Um um
these are just kind of some examples.
I have a friend who does loves Native
American art. He loves American history.
So, he deals in in these are some
pieces of his in Native American things.
Books, science fiction. Home decor is
a big thing. A lot of people love
watching the redo shows and and stuff like
that. >> If you like that, you'll get
training your eye and you'll go to a sale
and realize there's some really great
things. >> Yeah. And training your eye you
you you have your magnifying glass. >>
This is This is you have to have two
tools. Main tools. Or you can have a lot
of other things you can bring with you.
One is your loop, which is a magnifying
glass. >> Yeah. >> Um and I'll quit
shaking it so you can see
what I'm talking about. Um
and that is so you can see the marks on
things. You can see it up close. Is this
a painting or a print? Is it Lalique or
is it not? Is it whatever and you can
see it. And then you can make help you
make decision. The other one is your
Oracle which we call our phones. >> Yeah.
>> Because with that you and this is
happening at my estate sales more and
more. I see people that looking at
something and then they're in the corner
looking. >> Oh, taking pictures and
looking >> Yeah. >> can um Google Lens
are good ways to kind of shoot something
a picture of something and it'll bring
it up and give you what it is. Now you
got to be careful. They're about 70 to
80% accurate. >> Okay. >> Chat GPT tends
to want to tell you what you want to
hear. >> Oh yeah. >> But um and then uh of
course eBay. You can go to the completed
sales to get where the rubber hits the
road to see is that a really a good
buy or not. >> You also say to follow
auctions but but don't do anything
else. >> a great learning. If you have a
neighborhood auction, go and sit on your
hands. >> Yeah. >> And then you can see
what things are going for and what people
is hot in your neighborhood or hot in
your area and that's a great learning
experience. >> Uh okay, big tip number
two, start small. >> It is start small.
What you want to do is you don't want to
invest a ton of money. What you want to
do is start off and give yourself like a
weekend budget of say 50 to $100 and
you're going to find something. Don't buy
everything. There's a saying that says
it's better to pass a good deal than buy
a bad one. >> Sure. >> There's always
another good deal but it's going to take
you time to get rid of the bad one.
>> Yeah. And and you you you mentioned
follow the auction. Okay, got it. Mentioned
auction. Okay. All right. Um start
small and then where to sell them? >>
Where to sell is also then you'll want to
start seeing what Again, you're going to
find your own style of what's the type
of sales you like, what neighborhood you
want, what sort of things you want to
deal in. It's a bit of an experiment.
That's another reason for starting small
to see if this is something you really
want to do. >> Yeah. >> Once you get to a
certain point that God, I have a roll
on this. I'm making it. I suggest making
it into a genuine business. See an
accountant, get a business license and all.
Looking to sell um of course there's all
the all there's tons of on site. eBay's
the biggest of course and then there's
Etsy, Ruby Lane, all these others, and
more coming up all the time. But another
great thing is making friends with
people who are in the business, who
specialize. So, if you find a mid-century
rocker
for 20 bucks, you can take it to the
mid-century modern dealer, sell it to him
for 100 bucks. You've turned your 20
into 100. He's going to sell it for 300.
God bless him. He's paying the rent. He's
paying the you know. >> Also, you say
scaling up. >> Scaling up. Start small.
Make sure of what you want to do, that
this is really a business you want to
be in. And then you can kind of scale it
as you go on where you want to do. So,
you're training your eyes the big thing,
and then deciding what you want
to deal in, and then deciding
you know, and then it's all an experiment,
and you're constantly learning.
That's why I love the business. I love
the research and learning. >> You say to
keep notes and records cuz that's like
how you would do a business as well.
>> You run your You want to run it Once
you scale up and you're actually going
to run it, you want to keep good records.
You want to be able to make
sure you're making a profit.
You want to make sure that also by
getting a business license, your car, your
gas, other stuff is a business deduction.
So, it can take your overall household
income that comes off of your whole things
that you can't deduct if you're just
getting a paycheck. As a business, you
can now deduct. >> Also, too, when you
take notes, you kind of see what is
working and what isn't, right? >> Exactly.
>> What's selling and what's not >>
Exactly. And And again, it's learning. And
sometimes you take the notes and I paid
50 bucks for that, and you're and it was
a mistake. So, you you sold it for 40
just to get it out of the way eventually.
But you learn those. And you never hear
that from the dealer. They always tell
you about the the little elite glasses
they found but you know, they don't tell
you about the the other way around. >>
Yes, kind of like a gambler. They talk
about the big win, but they never tell
you about the big losses. >> Exactly. I
totally get it. And the most important
thing you say is have fun. So, there
there is It is. It's fun. >> Gary,
thank you so much. >> Thank you, Helen.
>> All right, we'll be right back
with more AM Northwest. Don't go away.
>> Excellent job, turkey. job, Turkey.